William Allen papers MS-916
Rauner Special Collections Library
William Allen papers
bulk
1800-1856
Rauner Special Collections Library
Allen, William
MS-916
.75 linear ft. 2 boxes
William Allen (DC Honorary 1812) contain correspondence, letters and documents related to Dartmouth University and the Dartmouth College Case, two unpublished books, a manuscript memoir, seven writings, leases and financial records, and miscellaneous notes and accounts. WA was a Dartmouth College trustee, President of the short-lived Dartmouth University, 1818-1819, and President of Bowdoin College, 1820-1838. The papers document his tenure as minister in Massachusetts, his college presidencies, and his retirement to Northampton, MA.
Scope and Contents
The papers of William Allen contain correspondence to and from Allen, letters and documents related to Dartmouth University and the Dartmouth College Case, two unpublished books, a manuscript memoir, seven writings, leases and financial records, and miscellaneous notes and accounts. The papers document his tenure as minister in Massachusetts, through his presidencies, and his retirement to Northampton, MA. The correspondence includes letters to and from John Wheelock (DC Class of 1771), Dartmouth College President and Trustee, 1779-1815; William Plumer, Governor of New Hampshire; Francis Brown (DC Class of 1805), Dartmouth College President and Trustee, 1815-1820; Daniel Dana (DC Class of 1788), Dartmouth College President and Trustee, 1820-1821; and Nathan Lord (DC Honorary 1821), Dartmouth College President and Trustee, 1828-1863. Of note in the collection is WA’s manuscript memoir on Samson Occom, the Mohegan Indian missionary, and the correspondence related to the Dartmouth College Case. The writings include an oration and a sermon on patriotism.
Related Materials
"An American Biographical and Historical Dictionary," by William Allen
Alumni 432a, Alumni 432b, Ticknor LAH .A5a, Ticknor LAH Ap5am, Ticknor LAH Ap5am c.2, Ticknor E176 .A435 c.2 Rauner Special Collections Library, Dartmouth College Library Reference E176 .A435 Baker/Berry Library, Dartmouth College Library
Documents relating to property given by Pres. Wheelock to Princeton Theological Seminary, March 28, 1799-August 14, 1844, v.p
Manuscript Codex 799228.1 Rauner Special Collections Library, Dartmouth College Library
Opinion in the case of Trustees of Dartmouth College v. Wm. H. Woodward by the United States Supreme Court
Manuscript Codex 001950 Rauner Special Collections Library, Dartmouth College Library
Papers of Salma Hale (DC Hon. 1849)
Rauner Special Collections Library, Dartmouth College Library Manuscript MS-933
Records of the Dartmouth University Treasurer, 1817-1820
Manuscript DA-90 Rauner Special Collections Library, Dartmouth College Library
Papers of John Wheelock (DC Class of 1771)
Rauner Special Collections Library, Dartmouth College Library Manuscript MS-934
Custodial History
Some of the William Allen papers were gifts from Mrs. Thomas C. Esty. Mr. Charles G. Milham donated one document to the papers. Another document was loaned by the New Hampshire Historical Society. Some of the papers were part of the Frederick Chase (DC Class of 1860) Collection given by his heirs. Several documents are photocopies and the originals are owned by the Pennsylvania Historical Society and the New Hampshire Historical Society. The provenance of the remaining papers is not known.
Conditions Governing Access
Unrestricted.
Allen, William
Biography
William Allen was born in Pittsfield, MA. on January 2, 1784. After graduating from Harvard University in 1802, he studied ministry for two years with his father, Rev. Thomas Allen, and the Rev. Dr. John Pierce of Brookline, MA. In 1804, Allen became licensed to preach. In 1805, he received his AM from Harvard and became Harvard University's assistant librarian and regent, a position he held until 1810. In 1810, he succeeded his father as pastor of the First Congregational Church of Pittsfield, MA. where he remained for seven years. In 1812, he received an honorary AM from Dartmouth College and in 1817, became Professor of Logic and Metaphysics at the newly established Dartmouth University under the presidency of his father-in-law John Wheelock (DC Class of 1771), former President and Trustee of Dartmouth College. After Wheelock’s death, Allen became the executor of the John Wheelock estate and succeeded his father-in-law as President of Dartmouth University in 1818. However, in 1819, Dartmouth University was disbanded by the Supreme Court ruling. Allen accepted the position of President of Bowdoin College in 1820 and moved to Brunswick, ME. As president of Bowdoin, he established a medical school at the college. In 1831, he was ejected from the presidency as a result of a Maine State Act, but was restored to office two years later. He resigned from Bowdoin in 1838 and retired to Northampton, MA. While at Northampton, he published the third edition of his "American Biographical and Historical Dictionary" (1857). Other works by Allen include "Junius Unmasked" (1828), a memoir of Eleazar Wheelock (1838), and two books of verse: "Wunnissoo, or the Vale of Hoosatunnuk, a Poem" (1856) and "Poems of Nazareth and the Cross" (1.866). William Allen died in Northampton, MA on July 16, 1868.
- Writings, 1800-1853; 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of writings by William Allen from his days as a college undergraduate to his retirement. These include books, accounts, a memorandum, notes, a sermon, an oration, and a manuscript memoir. The earlier book was written while WA was an undergraduate at Harvard University in Massachusetts. The other book appears to have been a preliminary for his later, larger works of historical and biographical sketches of American personages, of which three editions were published. The accounts include deeds of land, financial records and receipts for food, land, and various other items. The memorandum is a listing of the curricula of studies at Columbia University, Union College, and Harvard University. Since its date is circa 1818, it was probably written by WA for use in his role as President of Dartmouth University. The sermon and oration both are on the topic of patriotism.
  - Box: 1, 1800-1853 (Box 1)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Unrestricted
    Box: 1
    - Student assignment book: “Elements of Geometry”, 1800 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unpublished book: "Historical Biographical Sketches, November, 1807 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Financial and account papers, 1810-1845 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Memorandum of the curricula of studies at Columbia, Union, and Harvard, 1818 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Notes re: Nathaniel Hall’s account papers with the estate of Amos Wardwell, June 21, 1819 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Sermon: “On the Landing of the Pilgrims at Plymouth 22nd December 1620”, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Oration: “The Patriot Hampden”January 4, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Manuscript memoir: “Memoirs of Samson Occom the Mohegan Indian Missionary”, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Personal Correspondence, 1810-1838; 2
  This series consists of letters to and from family and personal acquaintances of William Allen. Writers include John Wheelock (DC Class of 1771), WA’s father-in-law; Mrs. Maria Malleville (Wheelock) Allen, WA’s wife and daughter of John Wheelock; and Dartmouth College alumni.
  - Box: 1, 1810-1838 (Box 1)
    Unrestricted.
    - Letter from Thayer, Gideon, et al. re: the ministry in Braintree, MA, 1810-06-20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence with Wheelock, John (DC Class of 1771) Dartmouth College President & Trustee 1779-1815, Dartmouth University President & Trustee 1815-1817, July 1812-December 1814 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with Allen, Mrs. Maria Malleville (Wheelock), July 1814-September 1816 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Letter from Ripley, Eleazar Wheelock (DC Class of 1800), 1815-08-09 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence re: Goodrich claim, May 1817-May 1819 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter to Patten, Mrs. Ruth (Wheelock), 1818-06-13 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Letter from Dana, Judah (DC Class of 1795), 1818-08-20 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Lease of house & land in Hartford, VT to Levi Bellows, 1818-10-10 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Letter from White, Allen Porter (DC Class of 1816), 1819-05-22 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Letter from Perkins, Cyrus (DC Class of 1800, Med. School 1802), Dartmouth University Trustee 1816-1819, Dartmouth University Treasurer 1817-1819, 1819-07-16 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence with Mason, Jeremiah (DC Hon. 1823), 1819-08 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Letter to Packard, H. and Bailey, J. accepting the presidency of Bowdoin College, 1820-01-29 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Letter to Pickering, William, 1820-03-03 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Letter to Cleaveland, Parker (DC Hon. 1823), 1820-03-08 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letter from Brewster, Amos Avery, 1821-04-18 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Letter from Richards, William, 1838-12-25 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Correspondence and documents related to Dartmouth College, the Dartmouth College Case, and Dartmouth University, 1815-1856; 3
  This series consists of letters and documents relating to WA’s involvement with Dartmouth College, Dartmouth University, and the Dartmouth College Case. This includes correspondence with Dartmouth College administration, papers, letters, and reports written by WA as President of Dartmouth University. Also found within this series is correspondence with Dartmouth College alumni, administrators of Dartmouth College and Dartmouth University, and the then current governor of New Hampshire, William Plumer, regarding the Dartmouth College Case.
  - Box: 1, 1815-1819 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence with Wheelock, John (DC Class of 1771), Dartmouth College President & Trustee 1779-1815, Dartmouth University President & Trustee 1815-1817, July 1815-December 1815 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Letter from Allen, Mrs. Maria Malleville (Wheelock), 1816-09-15 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Letter from Woodward, William Henry (DC Class of 1792), Dartmouth College Treasurer 1805-1816, Dartmouth University Treasurer 1816-1818, 1817-03-04 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence with Morse, Jedidiah, 1817-03 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence with Brown, Francis (DC Class of 1805), Dartmouth College President & Trustee 1815-1820, August 1817-July 1819 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Address to parents and friends of students, late members of Dartmouth, 1817-11-08 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Box: 2, 1770-1856 (Box 2)
    Box: 2
    - Notes re: Dartmouth University affairs, 1817-11-11 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence with Holmes, John, January-March 1818 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence with Hale, Salma (DC Hon. 1849), February-December 1818 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence with Plumer, William, Governor of New Hampshire, March 1818-March 1819 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Letter from Eastman, Moses (DC Class of 1794), 1818-04-07 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence with Lang, Richard, 1818-04-22 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Letter from Ripley, Major General T.W., 1818-08-14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Letter from Bartlett, Ichabod (DC Class of 1808), 1818-08-19 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Letter from Elkins, Jeremiah (DC Class of 1817), 1818-08-27 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Letter to Pinkney, William, 1818-09-10 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Letter to Sullivan, George, 1818-09-19 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Bill to the Dartmouth University Treasurer, 1818-1819 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence with Perkins, Cyrus (DC Class of 1800, Med. School 1802), Dartmouth University Trustee 1816-1819, Dartmouth University Treasurer 1817-1819, January 1819-February 1819 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Letter from Walcut, Thomas and Ticknor, Elisha (DC Class of 1783), 1819-02-17 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Notice to students and friends of Dartmouth University, 1819-03-01 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Letter from Nott, Eliphalet, 1819-03-10 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence with Marsh, Charles (DC Class of 1786), 1819-04 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Deposition re: the Dartmouth College Case, 1819-04-27 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Report to the Committee of Legislature, 1819-09-15 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Letter to the Committee of New Hampshire Legislation, 1820-05-05 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter to Farrar, Timothy (DC Class of 1807), Dartmouth College Librarian & Treasurer 1822-1826, 1824-01-07 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence with Lord, Nathan (DC Hon. 1821), Dartmouth College President and Trustee 1828-1863, July 1841-February 1856 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Material collected by Allen regarding the Dartmouth College case; lists, deeds, specification of charges, affidavits., 1770-1818 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Correspondence and documents related to the Wheelock estate, 1810-1836; 4
  This series contains letters to and from William Allen and documents written by WA as executor of the Wheelock estate. WA married the only child of John Wheelock, and so became the executor of John Wheelock’s estate. After his wife died in 1828, he became the legal guardian of his children, and thus, the executor of his children’s Wheelock estate. The papers in this series relate to WA’s function as executor of the Wheelock estate.
  - Box: 2, 1810-1839 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous notes and accounts re: Dartmouth University & Wheelock estate, August 1810-March 1839 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Letter to Morse, Jedidiah, 1817-04-05 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence with Miller, Samuel, February 1819-June 1822 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence with Olcott, Mills (DC Class of 1790), Dartmouth College Treasurer 1816-1822, August 1819-November 1819 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence with Ralston, Robert, March 1820-October 1826 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence with Codman, John, March-July 1820 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence with Dana, Daniel (DC Class of 1788), Dartmouth College President and Trustee 1820-1821, December 1823-June 1825 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Letter to Chester, N., 1826-10-15 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Papers re: WA’s children’s estate, July-August 1836 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Memorandum of dates of papers re: Princeton, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)